Eczema is a common
skin disease
and there are plenty of drugs
on the market to combat it.
But what about diet?
Are there foods
that trigger eczema,
and can dietary changes
be used to treat it?
Watch to find out.
"Best Foods to Avoid for Eczema &
Exclusion Diets for Eczema"
Eczema, also known
as atopic dermatitis,
is a chronic inflammatory
skin disease.
In fact, it’s the leading cause
of healthy years of life lost
due to common skin diseases,
because it’s just so common,
affecting up to
a fifth of us.
And, it's not just
an itchy rash;
it’s associated with
other diseases too.
Yes, it can be itchy, exhausting,
and embarrassing,
but in kids, it may
increase risk for ADHD,
though that may just be
from the sleep deprivation.
And, in adults, it may increase
the risk of major depression.
And, it’s on the rise.
There are drugs for it, of course;
there are always drugs.
Steroids are the
first-line therapy,
but then there are
immunosuppressants as well,
with more in the
drug pipeline.
You know the medical
profession is desperate
when they’re forced to go
back to the basics
and start applying
leeches to people.
Previously, I talked about
the safety and efficacy
of other, more
natural treatments,
but what about diet?
Our story begins in 1920, a year
doctors were realizing
how good this
oxygen stuff was,
though maybe not as good as
injecting people with mercury,
but a researcher at Johns Hopkins
reported a number of cases
in which by omitting eggs, meat,
and milk from the diet,
patients’ eczema improved.
Who’s going to profit
off of that though?
No wonder it took 58 years
before it was put to the test.
Figuring eggs and milk
were the two foods
most likely involved in eczema,
they excluded them—
and chicken and beef,
since it may just be chicken and
cow proteins more generally,
in a randomized double-blind
controlled trial
swapping in soy milk
instead, and…
70% of the patients
improved.
One person got worse on the no egg,
no chicken, no milk, no beef diet,
but almost everyone
else got better.
So, the researchers concluded
that for many kids,
avoiding those foods may
induce a clinical improvement.
And interestingly,
it didn’t seem to depend
on whether allergy tests showed
they were allergic to milk and eggs.
Either way, they tended
to get better, regardless.
You can do randomized double-blind
food challenges,
where you give kids with eczema
various foods in opaque capsules,
like one with egg powder,
one with wheat powder, etc.
Egg was found by far to be
the most offending food.
For example, in this study, where
they just cut out the eggs,
dramatic improvements
were documented
for both the amount of skin involvement
and the severity of the eczema lesions
after removing
eggs from the diet,
but in about 90% of cases,
the mom had no idea
that eggs were
a problem.
Why?
Because it wasn’t like they were
eating scrambled eggs or something.
Almost all the egg
exposure was hidden;
they were exposed to hidden
egg products in packaged foods.
So, they had no idea why their
eczema was so bad—
until this study, where they
removed all eggs
and egg products
from their diets.
Eggs are evidently the
most frequent cause
of food sensitivity
in children.
Out of hundreds of kids
with eczema tested,
egg allergy was documented in about
two-thirds of those with sensitivities.
In fact, a child having a blood
reaction to egg white proteins
appears to be one of the
best laboratory tests
for predicting future allergic
diseases in general.
It appears to be the ovomucoid
protein within egg whites
that seems to be causing
most of the mischief.
About 40% of kids with eczema
have some form of food allergy.
And, the more food
allergies they have,
the more likely it appears
they’re going to suffer
from eczema— and,
make it worse.
Those who react to
cows’ milk protein
are significantly more likely
to suffer severe eczema,
showing the important role
cows’ milk proteins may play
“in the induction and increased
severity of eczema in children.”
Often, parents switch from cows’
milk to goats’ milk,
in an attempt to improve
their children’s eczema.
But goats’ milk should never
be given to kids
with a cows’ milk allergy,
because they often cross-react
with one another,
which has been confirmed with double-blind
placebo controlled food challenges.
Ass milk, on the other hand,
is a different story.
Switching kids to donkey
milk improved their eczema,
and, for that matter, horse’s
milk might, as well.
The original randomized,
double-blind, controlled trial
of diet and eczema
found that cutting out
eggs, chicken, milk, and beef
significantly improved eczema in 70%
of the kids that
completed the study.
Subsequent studies
found similar results,
though in this case,
for example,
it only seemed to work for
a quarter of the kids.
But, bottom line,
out of 13 studies
on avoiding milk,
eggs, or both,
10 out 13 studies documented
overall clinical improvement.
The economic burden
of eczema
caused by just regular
cows’ milk formula alone
may be hundreds of millions
of dollars a year,
though eggs appear to be worse,
in terms of predicting persistence
and severity of the disease.
Sensitization to egg
white and cows’ milk
can occur even in breast-fed
infants though.
So, presumably the source
of the exposure
is the passage of egg
and cow proteins
through the mother’s milk,
but you don’t know until
you put it to the test.
New mothers were randomized
to cut out eggs,
cows’ milk, and fish
from their diet
during the first three months
of breastfeeding
after giving birth or to
continue their regular diet.
And indeed, the
infants of mothers
who cut out the eggs,
milk, and fish
were significantly less likely
to have eczema by age 6 months,
though after that age, the
decreased rates of eczema
in the no eggs/milk
or fish group
were no longer
statistically significant.
Follow those same kids
out to four years, though,
and those whose
moms cut out the eggs,
milk, and dairy for
just three months
while breast feeding
had significantly
lower eczema rates
even years later.
Consuming that hypoallergenic
diet during breastfeeding
cut child eczema
rates in half.
Eating more plant
foods may also help.
The majority of fruit
and vegetable studies
suggest that higher consumption
by mothers during pregnancy,
and children in
early life,
results in reductions
in asthma,
another allergic-
type disease.
Maybe it’s the phenolic phytonutrients
in plants that are helping,
supported by evidence that
certain vegetarian diets
appear to alleviate
the severity
of skin diseases in
adults with eczema.
Though if you look
at that citation,
it was a very
strange diet.
They found striking
benefits in terms
of reducing the
severity of eczema,
and even 2 months after
they went off the diet,
they were still doing better
than when they started,
but the diet was
just vegetable juice,
brown rice, kelp, tofu,
tahini, and persimmon leaf tea,
and severely
calorie-restricted.
And, just straight fasting
alone can improve eczema,
as can a strictly
plant-based diet,
which is not so
surprising given the data
on children showing
how much better
they can do cutting
out eggs and dairy.
In spite of these data,
dermatologists
and pediatricians have,
for many years,
denied the role of
food in eczema,
even though as many as
80% of kids may benefit
cutting out milk
and/or eggs
regardless of what the
various allergy tests show.
You can’t necessarily tell
if diet is going to help,
until you yourself put it
to the test in your own body.
And, that’s what
parents are doing.
They’re not waiting for
their pediatricians to catch up;
75% of parents with
eczema-stricken kids
have tried some form
of dietary exclusion,
most commonly cutting
out dairy and eggs,
though only about
40% of parents
who tried it feel
that it worked.
But hey, why not
give it a try?
A typical recommendation you
see in the medical literature is,
“Look, if you have a
child with some bad eczema,
and the drugs
aren’t working,
then... why don’t you try
cutting out some foods?”
But, that seems
to me backwards.
If foods are
contributing,
why not treat
the cause
and eliminate the
offending foods,
and then do the drugs
if diet isn’t enough.
Now, there are some pretty
nutty eczema diets out there,
like the so-called
“few foods” diet,
excluding everything
except lamb, potatoes,
Rice Krispies, broccoli,
and pears.
To my surprise, it was
actually put to the test—
I told you docs
were desperate!
But it failed to
show a benefit.
Basically, if you don’t know
where to begin,
the simplest approach may be to
just cut out dairy and eggs
and see what happens.
That’s a controversial
recommendation, though.
Avoiding fish, beef,
eggs, and dairy
without medical
supervision?
That might trigger
malnutrition-related pathology.
What?!
I checked out
that citation,
and it's just another article
making an unsupported claim.
Now, if you exclude everything,
like 99% of your diet
is rice milk, well then, obviously,
that’s completely insufficient,
but for most parents,
the #1 thing they add
to their child’s diet for
eczema... is vegetables,
and the #1 thing they cut
down on is.... junk food,
and I don’t think
we have to worry,
about a junk
food deficiency.